<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the most materiall parts of Dr. Hamond's booke of schisme: or a defence of the Church of England, against exceptions of the Romanists written in a letter from a Catholique gent. to his friend in England.</title>
            <author>B. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220298</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831717</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56416)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2051:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the most materiall parts of Dr. Hamond's booke of schisme: or a defence of the Church of England, against exceptions of the Romanists written in a letter from a Catholique gent. to his friend in England.</title>
                  <author>B. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed anno Dom. 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: B.P. Brussels the 30 March, 1654.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Hammond, Henry.  Of schisme a defence of the Church of England against the exceptions of the Romanists.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hammond, Henry, 1605-1660. --  Of schisme a defence of the Church of England against the exceptions of the Romanists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36184:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To the moſt materiall parts of D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> HAMOND'S Booke of <hi>Schiſme:</hi> Or a defence of the Church OF ENGLAND, Againſt exceptions of the <hi>Romaniſts:</hi> Written in A Letter from a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Gent. to his friend in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:36184:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36184:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER To the moſt materiall parts of Doctor <hi>Hamonds</hi> Book of <hi>Schiſme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have been pleaſed to ſend me Doctor <hi>Hamonds</hi> Book of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> or a defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt the exceptions of the Romaniſts, as alſo your letters, wherein you lay Commands on me to read it, and thereupon to give you my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: truly Sir, both the one and the other could never have come to me in better ſeaſon, for having heard from ſom of my friends in <hi>England</hi> a good while ſince of another book, written by one Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, as alſo one lately come out of the Biſhop of <hi>Deries,</hi> and of this which you have ſent me, I was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36184:3"/>wondering what thoſe who call themſelves of the Church of <hi>England</hi> could ſay to defend them from Schiſme, but now your favour in letting me ſee this of Doctor <hi>Hammonds,</hi> I am freed from my bondage, and ſatisfied in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that the moſt can adde little to what hath been upon that ſubject of Schiſme ſaid by him, whom you ſtile wiſe and learned, and well may he be ſo, but here he hath failed, as all men muſt that take in hand to defend bad lawes, which I think to make appeare to you or any indifferent Judge, and which I will doe rather upon ſome obſervations of ſeverall paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in his booke then conſideration of the whole, which I will leave for ſome other who hath more leaſure, in the meane time I muſt ſay with the Poet, ſpeaking of ſome Lawyers in his time, <hi>Fures, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Pedio, Pedius quid? Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina raris libratin Antithetis:</hi> The Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique ſayes to Doctor <hi>Hamond,</hi> You are an Heretick, you are a Schiſmatick, &amp; Doctor <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> replies good Engliſh, ſome Criticiſmes, much greefe, with many citations out of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity indifferent to both parts of the queſtion: but to draw neere your ſatisfaction: his firſt Chap. is for the body of it common to both parts,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> yet I cannot omit one ſtrange peece of logick at the end of it, where he concludeth, that the occaſion or motive of Schiſme is not to be conſidered, but only the fact of Schiſme,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36184:3"/>of which poſition I can ſee no connection to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny premiſes going before, and it ſelfe is a pure contradiction, for not a diviſion but a cauſeleſſe diviſion is a Schiſme and how a diviſion can be ſhewed to be unreaſonable, and cauſeleſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining the occaſions, and motives, I do not underſtand, nor (with his favour) as I think he himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Much of the ſecond Chap. is likewiſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> only he ſlightly paſſeth over the diſtinction of Hereſie and Schiſme, as if he would not have it underſtood that all Hereſie is Schiſme, though ſome Schiſme be no Hereſie,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> againe treating of Excommunication he eaſily ſlideth over this part, that wilfull continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in a juſt Excommunication maketh Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, what he calls Mr. <hi>Knolls</hi> Conceſſion, I take to be the publique profeſſion of the Roman, or Catholique Church, and that nature it ſelfe teacheth all rationall men, that any Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that can lye, and knoweth not whether it doth lye or no, in any propoſition: cannot have power to bind any particular to beleeve what ſhe ſayeth, neither can any man of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding have an obligation to beleeve what ſhee teacheth <hi>farther then agrees with the rules of his owne reaſon:</hi> Out of which it followeth, that the Roman Churches binding of men to a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith (which the Proteſtants and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hereticall multitudes have likewiſe uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped) if ſhe be infallible, is evidently gentle, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36184:4"/>right, and neceſſary, as contrariwiſe in any other Church or Congregation, which pretends not to infallibility, the ſame is unjuſt, tyrannicall, and a ſelfe-condemnation to the binders: ſo that the ſtate of the queſtion will be this, Whether the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique or Roman Church, be infallible or no, for ſhee pretendeth not to bynd any man to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets or beleefs upon any other ground or title. By this you may perceive much of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe—to be not only ſuperfluous and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary,</hi> but contrary to himſelfe, for he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth to perſwade that the Proteſtant may be certaine of ſome truth, againſt which the Roman Catholique Church bindeth to profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of error, which is as much to ſay as he who pretendeth to have no infallible rule, by which to govern his Doctrine ſhall be ſuppoſed to be fallible, and he that pretendeth to have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule ſhall be ſuppoſed to be fallible: at moſt becauſe fallible objections are brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, now then conſider what a meeke and humble Son of the Church ought to do, when of the one ſide is the authority of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>and poſſeſsion (ſuch antiquity and poſſeſsion without diſpute or contradictions from the adverſarie, as no King can ſhew for his Crowne, and much leſſe any other perſon or perſons for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing)</hi> the perſwaſion of infallibility; all the pledges that Chriſt hath left to his Church for motives of Union: on the other ſide <hi>uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> reaſons <hi>of a few men pretending to learning
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36184:4"/>every day contradicted by incomparable numbers of men wiſe and learned,</hi> and thoſe few men confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe reaſons, and themſelves uncertaine, fallible, and ſubject to error, certainly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a bias of intereſt, or prejudice, it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to leave the Church if he be in it, or not returne if he be out of it: for if infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility be the ground of the Churches power to command beleefe, as ſhe pretends no other, no time, no ſeperation within memory of Hiſtory, can juſtifie a continuance out of the Church: You may pleaſe to conſider then, how ſolid this Doctors diſcourſe is, who telleth us, for his great evidence that he (ſaith he) who do not acknowledge the Church of Rome to be infallible, may be allowed to make cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuppoſitions (that follow there) The queſtion is whether a Proteſtant be a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, becauſe a Proteſtant; and he will prove he is not a Sciſmatique, becauſe he goeth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to Proteſtant, that is Schiſmaticall grounds: I pray you reflect, that not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Church to be infallible is that for which we charge the Doctor with Schiſme, and Haereſie in <hi>Capite,</hi> and more then for all the reſt <hi>he holds diſtinct from us,</hi> for this principle taketh away all beleefe, and all ground of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and turneth it into uncertainty and Weather-cock opinion, putteth us iuto the condition to be <hi>circumferri omni vento Doctrinae,</hi> fubmitteh us to Atheiſm and all ſort of miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancie,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36184:5"/>Let him not then over leape the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but either prove this is not ſufficient to make him a Schiſmatick <hi>(i)</hi> and an heritique too, let him acknowledge he is both.</p>
            <p>In his third Chap. what is cheefely to be noted to our purpoſe, is, that his diviſion is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, for he maketh Schiſme to be only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Monarchicall power or againſt frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall charity, which is very much beſides the principles of thoſe Proteſtants who pretend ſo much to the authority of Councells, me thinks he ſhould have remembred there might be Schiſme againſt Conſiliatory, authority, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be called ſo when the Councel actually ſitteth, or in the unanimity of beleefe in the diſperſion of the Churches, ſo that the Doctor (ſuppoſing he concluded againſt the Pope) hath not concluded himſelf no Schiſmatick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeparated from the Catholique world, in this Chap. he telleth us many things, ſome true, ſome not ſo, but all either Common to us both, or not appertaining to the controverſie, untill he concludes that certainly the Roman Patriarchie did not extend it ſelfe to all ſtately and this he does out of a word in <hi>Rufinus,</hi> which he ſuppoſeth to be taken in a ſpeciall proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Law, whereas indeed that Authors know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Grammar was not ſuch as ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily exact any ſuch beleefe, eſpecially lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men ſaying the contrary.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36184:5"/>
            <p>Than he telleth you that the Office of Primats and Patriarchs was the ſame,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> only authorizing that affirmation from an Epiſtle of Anacletus,<note place="margin">He urgeth <hi>Gratian</hi> too.</note> the which as ſoon as occaſion ſerveth, he will tell you is of no Authority, but fictitious, then he ſaith there was no power over the Patriarchs, his proof is becauſe the Emperor <hi>uſed his ſecular Authority in gathering of Councels,</hi> concluding that becauſe the Pope did not gather general Councels, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had no Authority over the Univerſal Church, which how unconſequent that is, I leave to your judgment, but I muſt not forget here what I omitted to inſert before, that in his diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſchiſm he omitteth the principal, if not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, &amp; in the uſe of the word by the Antients, the only ſchiſm which is when one breaketh from the whole Church of God, for though a breach made from the immediate ſuperiour, or a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, may in ſome ſort, and in our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner of ſpeaking be called a ſchiſm, yet that by which one breaketh away from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the whole Church, is properly, and in a higher ſence called ſchiſm, and is that out of which the preſent queſtion proceedeth, whereas other diviſions, as long as both parts remain in communion with the univerſal Church, are not properly ſchiſms, but with a diminutive particle, ſo that in this diviſion he left out that part which appertained to the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>In the fourth Chapter he pretendeth to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether by Chriſt his donation Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36184:6"/>had a primacy over the Church, where not to reflect upon his curious diviſion, I cannot omit that he remembers not what matters he handles, when he thinketh the Catholick ought to prove, that his Church, or Pope hath an Univerſal Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for it being granted that in England the Pope was in quiet poſſeſſion of ſuch a Primacie, the proof that it was juſt, belongeth not to us more then to any K. who received his Kingdom from his Anceſtors, a time out of mind, to prove his pretenſion to the Crown juſt: for quiet poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it ſelf is a proof, until the contrary be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced: as who ſhould Rebel againſt ſuch a King were a Rebel, until he ſhewed ſufficient cauſe for quitting obedience; with this difference, that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to a King may by preſcription or bargain be made unneceſſary, but if Chriſt hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded obedience to his Church, no length of years, nor change of humane affairs can ever quit us from this duty of obedience, ſo that the charge of proving the Pope to have no ſuch Authority from Chriſt, lyeth upon the Proteſtants now as freſhly, as the firſt day of the breach, and wil do ſo until the very laſt, as for his proofs which he cals evidences,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> he telleth us firſt that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was the Apoſtle of the Circumciſion <hi>excluſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to the Uncircumciſion, or Gentiles to prove this, he ſaith the Apoſtles diſtributed their great Univerſal Province into ſeveral <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, by his interpretation, leſſer Provinces, and citeth <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 25. where Saint <hi>Peter</hi> with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36184:6"/>other Apoſtles prayeth God to ſhew which of the two propoſed, he was pleaſed to have promoted to the dignity of being an Apoſtle, this they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and this rigorous interpreter ſaith, it ſignifies the ſpecial Province <hi>Saint Matthias</hi> was to have, though the Scripture it ſelf expreſſeth the contrary, ſaying the effect was that afterward, he was counted amongſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, could any man not blinded with error make ſo wretched an interpretation? but he goes on pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently adding that <hi>Saint Peter</hi> in the ſame place calleth theſe particular provinces <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and will you know what this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place is, read the Text, and you ſhall find that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>Judas</hi> his going to Hell to receive his eternal damnation: Me thinks you ſhould wonder I can go on without aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at ſuch blaſphemous explications, for ſure it can be no leſs, ſo to abuſe the Word of God, and after this what do you expect? His poſition is as directly againſt Scripture, as if he had done it on purpoſe, the Scripture telling us how by a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Viſion Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was commanded to preach to <hi>Cornelius</hi> a Gentile, firſt of all the Apoſtles, and himſelf in the Councel of Jeruſalem proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, and yet this Doctor can teach he was made Apoſtle to the Jews; excluſively to the Gentiles, though all ſtory ſay the contrary; Again, if he were made the Apoſtle of the Jews excluſively to the Gentiles, by the ſame reaſon St. <hi>Paul</hi> was made Apoſtle of the Gentiles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſively
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36184:7"/>to the ſence, for the words are like, and yet the Scripture teacheth us that where ever he came,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> he preached firſt to the ſence; is not this to make Scripture ridiculous? but he goes on telling us that the Gentiles excluſively to the Circumciſion were the lot of St. <hi>Paul</hi> by Saint <hi>Peters</hi> own confeſſion, <hi>his words are for the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, or Gentiles they were not Saint Peters pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, but peculiarly Saint Pauls, &amp;c.</hi> but look on the place, and you ſhall find no word of excluſion as the word peculiarly is, and wheron lyeth the whole queſtion, ſo that the Doctors Evidence is his own word againſt the main torrent of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on either ſide. Again, ſee how he wrongs <hi>St. Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect: <hi>8, 9.</hi>
               </note> and his Jewiſh profelites, where he ſaies he withdrew from all communion with the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Chriſtians. Whereas the Text expreſſeth no more, then that he withdrew from eating with them, that is, keeping the Gentile diet: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this wiſely laid ground, he would perſwade us followed the diviſion of the Biſhoppricks both in <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> but bringing not one word of antiquity proving this to have been the cauſe,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> yet is he ſo certain of it, that he will find a collonie of Jews even in <hi>England,</hi> for fear <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſhould have touched a Gentile, and yet he cites Saint <hi>Proſper,</hi> that both Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and St: <hi>Paul</hi> founded the Church of Gentiles in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſecond Evidence he bringeth from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Keyes,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> which he ſayeth were given equally to the Apoſtles, <hi>Matt:</hi> 28. yet confeſſeth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36184:7"/>the Keyes were eſpecially promiſed to Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Matt:</hi> 16. but performed only in common, <hi>Matt:</hi> the 28. which though they may be both true, yet is abſurdly ſaid, for who acknowledgeth a ſpecial promiſe, ſhould have found out a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al performance which is done, <hi>Joh:</hi> 21. Again,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> he would perſwade the World that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church holdeth, none had the Keyes but Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> calling it a peculiarity, and incloſure of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as if the other Apoſtles had them not, which is calumnie, I cannot paſs without noting another old interpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in his 20 Sect: out of <hi>Matthew</hi> the 19. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the 12 Thrones at the day of Judgment, he explicates to rule, or preſide in the Church, his quibling about the Word is ſo light a thing, as it is not worth conſideration, the ſence being plain that upon <hi>Peter</hi> the Church was built ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, though not with excluſion of others.</p>
            <p>In the fifth Chapter,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> firſt he lightly paſſeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the two moſt conſiderable Texts of Scripture fit to be alledged for Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacy, viz. <hi>Feed my Sheep,</hi> and thou art <hi>Peter:</hi> becauſe they have no appearance, and have been often anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Why no appearance? becauſe he and his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows ſay ſo, and is if being as often repeated, was not as likely to ſhew the anſwer was naught, as the anſwering to impeach the Objector: but who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the principles of Catholick Faith, knows that as well for other points of our Faith, as for this of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſupremacy, we relie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36184:8"/>not only upon ſuch places of Scripture; next he urgeth that if the ſucceſſion to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> were the baſe of the Popes ſupremacie,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antioch</hi> ſhould be the chief See, becauſe <hi>St: Peter</hi> ſat there, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to omit his firſt and ſecond queſtion, whereof the firſt is untrue, I anſwer to the third Negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the couſtituting a Church, and Biſhop at <hi>Antioch</hi> before at <hi>Rome,</hi> did confer no priviledg extraordinary on that Church, and the reaſon is clearly deduced out of his ſecond Quaere, becauſe it was before <hi>Rome,</hi> for he could not give any ſuch Authority, but by deveſting himſelf, ſince there cannot be two heads to one body, therefore this Authority and priuiledg of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> can reſt,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> &amp; be no where but where he dyed. Then he tels you that the dignity, or precedence of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſurely much more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deduced by the Councel of Calcedon from this, that <hi>Rome</hi> was then the Imperial City, or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Reſidence of the Emperor: a very wiſe Judgment, that the quality upon which the unity, that is, the ſafety of the Church Univerſal relies, ſhould be planted upon a bottom fallible, and ſubject to fail, but the reſolution was ſo ſhameful that the very Patriarch was aſhamed, &amp; imputed it to his ambitious Clergy, who how tumultuary, and untuly they were, is to be ſeen in the Acts of the Councel.</p>
            <p>Seventhly,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> he cavilleth at the priviledg of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtracy, calling it a method of ſecurity beyond all amulets: then he tels us of Antiochs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36184:8"/>being equal to <hi>Rome,</hi> and that Conſtantinople de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired but the ſame priviledges againſt the very nature of the ſtory, for Conſtantinople being then a Patriarchy, if that made it equal to <hi>Rome</hi> as this Doctor faineth, what did it pretend <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for? ſeeing the Dr. aſſumes before that all Patriarchs were equal, neither <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and leſs Antioch had cauſe to complain.</p>
            <p>As for the Canon of <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> touching the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> it plainly ſheweth that the Metropolitans were ſubordinate to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, ſeeing this caſe of <hi>Cyprus</hi> was a peculiar ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted caſe, the reaſon given doth ſhew that the ſuperiority of Patriarchs was by cuſtom received from their Anceſtors, contrary to that which the Dr: before affirmed, however it is ſtill nothing to the purpoſe, becauſe the Authority which we ſay belongs to the Pope is neither Patriarchall nor derived from any inſtitution, or cuſtom of the Church, but from the inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Then he goes on with two examples,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> in which he would perſwade us that <hi>Juſtiniana prima,</hi> and <hi>Carthage</hi> were made exempt Cities by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, and ſeeth not that his own inſtance giveth the anſwer, for as in the temporal donation, he doth not exempt them from his own ſubjection, ſo neither from the Popes, in ſpiritual, nay nor as much as giveth them the ſtile of Patriarchs; though the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in his own City ordinarily had it.<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>In his 6. Chapter he examineth another title
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:36184:9"/>peculiar to <hi>England.</hi> viz: that our Nation was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by misſion from <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect: <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and this is totally beſide the queſtion, for no man is ſo ſtupid as to pretend Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> or the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to have power over the Univerſal Church, becauſe his ſucceſſors converted <hi>England:</hi> But ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a ſpecial title of gratitude; the violation of which aggravateth the ſin of ſchiſmatizing from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in our Nation, yet no man as far as I can underſtand thinks this latter Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of ſo high a nature, as that for no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or never ſo great cauſe, it may not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſed with, but only preſs it, then when the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is ſlighted,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> or by colourable arguments to the contrary unworthily avoided, and yet this Doctor quite miſtaking the queſtion fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth an Argument, as ful of words as emptie of matter, affirming there cannot be two ſuccesſive titles to poſſesſion of the ſame thing, telling us, that he who claimeth a Reward as of his own la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and travel, muſt diſclaim a donation, &amp;c. if any paſſed before, and that if a King have right by deſcent, he cannot claim any thing by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, by which you may ſee his underſtanding the Law is not much more <hi>then his underſtanding of our principles,</hi> but to come to ſome matter.</p>
            <p>His firſt Argument is that this Iſland was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted before Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> ſurely he means by the name of Iſleland, the Land and Mountains, and Trees, for it he ſpeak of the Men what hath the converſion of the former Iſlanders
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36184:9"/>to do with the ſubjection, and duty which the Saxons owe.</p>
            <p>His next Argument demandeth whether al that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> converted,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> were obliged to be under him, truly if it were to purpoſe I beleeve there might be proof that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expected it, but he doth not remember that he could us Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo it cometh to the ſame queſtion, but indeed he quite miſſeth the matter, for no body ſtateth this for the Popes ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but aggravation of the ſciſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly: He ſaid it was in the Emperors power to conſtitute Patriarchs: whether that be ſo or not,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> it will not be much to our purpoſe to diſpute here, only this I ſay, that he ſeems neither to underſtand the queſtion, nor proves what he would, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth nor the queſtion, which hath no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancie on the nature of Patriarchs, or rearms of gratitude, but on the donation of Chriſt, he proves not what he would, for he produceth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the act of an Emperor accounted tyrannical to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Church, without proof, or diſcuſsion whether it was wel or ill done, which was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make good his proof, neither doth he ſay whether the thing were done or no by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Biſhops, eſpecially ſince the Pope was an actor in the buſineſs, he addeth an Apocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal Decree of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the third, for giving of priviledges purely Eccleſiaſtical to the Bp: of <hi>Havenna,</hi> which out of his liberality he makes a Patriarch, but on the whole matter this is to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36184:10"/>be obſerved, that generally the Biſhops conſents were pre-demanded, or pre-ordered, as in the counſel of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> can 17. it is ordered that the Church ſhould tranſlate their Biſhopricks ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Emperors changing of his City, and when the Emperors did it, it is ſaid they did it according to the power given them, to wit, by the Church, ſo that a few examples to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary produced in the Raigns of headſtrong, and tyrannical Princes, <hi>as the moſt of thoſe were noted to be, under whom they are urged,</hi> and as they did: The Conqueror was prov'd nothing, and if they did, yet cannot they be taken as teſtimonies, when theſe matters of fact are only ſo attributed to Princes, as no way to exclude the Church: but whatſoever it was, it doth not at all appertian to the queſtion, ſince the Popes authority <hi>in the ſence he cals him Pope,</hi> is not properly patriarchal, nor hath any dependencie upon, or from, change of places <hi>made by the command of Printes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his 7th. Chap. he intends a juſtification of the breach,<note place="margin">Begun in <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> whereof as he doth not teach the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous occaſion, and how to his dying day the ſame King deſired to be reconciled, as alſo that it was but the coming two days ſhort of a Poſt to <hi>Rome,</hi> which hindered that the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement was not actually made, as may be ſeen in my Lo: of Charberies book, fol. 368: and that the moderate Proteſtants curſe the day wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it was made, ſo the very naming of <hi>H:</hi> 8th. is enough to confute all his diſcourſe, one of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36184:10"/>darlings of his Daughter having given him ſuch a character as hath ſtamped him for <hi>Englands Nero</hi> to future poſterity,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Walter Raughley</hi> in Preface to Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the World.</note> and as it was ſaid of <hi>Nero</hi> in reſpect of Chriſtian Religion: ſo might it be of him reſpecting the unity of the Church, <hi>viz:</hi> it muſt be a great good, which he began to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute and aboliſh: and as for the Acts paſſed in the Univerſities Convocation or Parlament, let the blood ſhed by that Tyrant bear witneſs what voluntary and free Acts they were, eſpecially thoſe two upon his <hi>Seneca</hi> and <hi>Burbey,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Fiſher,</hi> and the Chancellor <hi>More,</hi> that he might want nothing of being throughly parallel'd to <hi>Nero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But me thinks the Doctor differs not much in this, ſeeming tacitly to grant the Biſhops were forced, awed by that noted ſword in a ſlender threed, the <hi>praemunire,</hi> which did hang over their heads, though in the concluſion of that <hi>Sect:</hi> he ſaies we ought to judge charitably, <hi>viz.</hi> that they did not judge for fear nor temporal Intereſts: yet after waves the advantage of that charitable judgment, &amp; ſaith, That if what was determined were falſly determined by the King and Biſhops, then the voluntary and free doing it will not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, and if it were not, then was there truth in it antecedent to, and abſtracted from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, and it was their duty ſo to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and conclude that they were unwilling: laying the whole weight of the Argument upon this, that the pretentions for the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36184:11"/>in <hi>England</hi> muſt be founded either as Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the Univerſal Paſtorſhip of the Church, ſo including <hi>England</hi> as a Member thereof, or upon paternal right reſpecting St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> converſion, or upon concesſion from ſome of our Kings, &amp;c. To which I anſwer, that we relye on the firſt as the foundation and corner ſtone of the whole building. On the 3d. as an action worthy the Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which requires a gratefull conſideration from us. And on the 3d. not as a conceſſion, but as a juſt acknowledgment of what was neceſſarie to the good of Chriſtian Religion, taught our Kings by thoſe who taught them Chriſtian Religion; of which belief, I mean that the Pope as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to <hi>St. Peter</hi> is head and governor of the univerſal Church, we have been in poſſeſſion ever ſince the converſion of our Engliſh Anceſtors, then <hi>Saxons,</hi> to the Chriſtian Religion made by <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk ſent hither by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> for that purpoſe: untill that good King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, out of ſcrupuloſitie of conſcience (no doubt) was pleaſed to cut the guordian knot of thoſe bonds within which all his Anceſtors li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves; neither ſhal al that the Doct. and his fellows have ſaid, or can ſay, juſtifie themſelves ſo, but that ſuch a poſſeſſion as I here ſpeak of will convince them of ſchiſm, though all thoſe replyes which by ours have been 40 times made to everie one of thoſe Arguments the Doct, uſes ſhold bear but equal weight in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:36184:11"/>ſcale, which we think hoyſes it up into the air, for the arguments muſt be demonſtrative &amp; clear to men of common ſence, that muſt overthrow ſuch a poſſeſſion; and therefore it is that the Puritans who are much leſs friends to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> then to the Church of <hi>England</hi> were all diſputing out of Antiquity, and confeſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Napier</hi> on the Revelation.</note> that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath born a ſway with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any debatable contradiction over the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world 1260 yeers, a time that no King in the world can pretend to by ſucceſſion from his Anceſtors for poſſeſsion of his Crown, and yet I beleeve the Doctor would conclude thoſe Subjects guilty of Rebellion, which ſhould go about to deprive ſuch a King of his Crown, though he could not ſhew writings evidently concluding for him 13, 14, 15, or 1600 yeer ago, how much more if he could ſhew them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating his right in the interpretation of as wiſe and learned men as the world hath, and 20 times the numbers of their adverſaries:<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Queen <hi>Maries</hi> titular retaining of the Supremacie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſhe could diſpoſe the diſordered hearts of her ſubjects to get it peaceably revoked, is no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for the Doctor, ſhe never pretending it to be lawfully done, but that ſhe could not do otherwiſe, and by the refuſing of a Legat which in all Catholick times and Countreys hath been practiſed and thought lawfull,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> King <hi>Edward</hi> a childe of nine yeers old fell into the hands of wicked ambitious Traitors, who knowing the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36184:12"/>Kingdom affected for Religions ſake to Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to cut off her ſucceſsion and introduce their own, thought fit to ſtrengthen their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which beſides what they might hope from abroad, conſiſted of many <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> at home; thoſe two Sects having by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of that rupture in <hi>H:</hi> the 8th. time, ſpread and neſtled themſelves in many parts of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect: <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> being by Act of Parlament recorded a baſtard, and ſo pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by two Popes, and therefore miſtruſting all her Catholick Subjects who ſhe feared did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> title, in which ſhe was then likely to be ſupported by the King of <hi>France</hi> her Husband, was by the adviſe of men partly infected with <hi>Calviniſme</hi> or <hi>Lutheraniſme,</hi> partly ambitious of making their fortunes caſt upon that deſperate Councell of changing Religion, deſperate, I ſay, for ſee amongſt what a number of Rocks ſhe was, in conſequence of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel forced to ſail, witneſs her adhearing to the Rebels of all her neighbour Kings, ſo provoking them thereby as if the <hi>French</hi> King had not been taken out of this world, and winde and weather fought againſt the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado, in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſhe had been ruined, eſpecially her Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Subjects being ſo provoked as they were by moſt cruel and bloodie Laws; but this by the by: though from hence the Reader may judge of reaſon of changing Religion in her time, and what a ſolid foundation the Church of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:36184:12"/>hath, how far Mr. <hi>Maſon</hi> can juſtifie the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Biſhops,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> I will not now examine; but certain it is that the Record, (if there be ſuch a one) hath a great prejudice of being forged, ſince it lay ſome fifty yeers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known amongſt the Clamors againſt the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant fact, and no permiſſion given to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks to examine the ingenuitie of it, but howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is nothing to our purpoſe, for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever materiall miſsion they had by an externall conſecration, thoſe Biſhops who are ſaid to have conſecrated them are not as much as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have given them order to preach the Doctrine, or exerciſe the Religion they after did, which is the true meaning and effect of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I cannot end without nothing in his 20 <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra:</hi> the foundation upon which he himſelf ſaies his whole defires relyes: which is that becauſe the receſsion from the Romane Church was done by thoſe by whom, and to whom onely the power of right belonged legally, <hi>viz:</hi> the King and Biſhops of this Nation, therefore it is no ſchiſm, that is, whatſoever the reaſon of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath been even to turn <hi>Turks,</hi> or for viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting never ſo fundamental points of Religion, yet it had not been ſchiſm.</p>
            <p>In his 8th. Chapter as far as I underſtand, he divideth ſchiſm into formal, that is, breach of Unitie; and material, that is, breach of Doctrine or Cuſtoms, in which the Church was united: the former he brancheth into ſubordination to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36184:13"/>the Pope,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> of which enough hath been ſaid; and breach of the way provided by Chriſt for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the unity of Faith, the which he puts in many ſubordinations without any effect. For let us as he,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> if inferior Clergie men, diſſent from their own Biſhops, but not from their Metra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan in matter of Faith is it ſchiſm? he will anſwer, No: if a Metrapo itan diſſent from his Primate, but agree with the reſt of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, is it ſchiſm? I think he muſt ſay, No: if a Patriarch diſſent from the firſt, but agree with the reſt, is it ſchiſme? No: if a Nation, or a Biſhop diſſent from the reſt of the generall Councell, is it ſchiſm? ſtill I beleeve he will anſwer, No: where then is ſchiſm provided againſt? or where truly is there any ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Faith? if none of theſe are ſubject, and bound to their ſuperiors or Univerſals in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith. But, ſaith the Doctor, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles reſolved upon ſome few heads of ſpeciall force and efficacie to the planting of Chriſtian life, through the world, and preaching, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiting them in every Church of their planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Truly I do not know what a Catholick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth more, ſo that by the word few he meaneth enough to form a Religion, and Chriſtian life, and will ſhew us a Church which hath not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the truſt depoſited; for if there be none, what availeth this depoſiting? if there be any, clear it is that it preſerved it by tradition, if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36184:13"/>there be a queſtion whether it hath or no; again, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to what purpoſe was the depoſiting, ſo that if the Doctor would ſpeak aloud, I doubt he would be ſubject to as much jealouſie, as he ſaith <hi>Grocius</hi> was, I cannot but admire indeed the great temper he profeſſeth men of his Religion have, in chuſing of Doctrines, to wit,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> their ſubmisſion to the three firſt Ages, and the foure firſt Councels, but I confeſſe it is a humility, <hi>I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not,</hi> firſt to profeſs, they know not whether their teachers ſay true, or no, (that is, that they are fallible) and then to hold under pain of damnation what they ſay. Another peece of their Humility is in ſubmitting to Ages, where very few Witneſſes can be found, in regard of the rarity of the Authors, and the little occaſion they had to ſpeak of preſent controverſies. A third note of Humility is, that whereas the fourth Councel was held about the midſt of the fifth Age, theſe lovers of truth will ſtand to it, but not to the fourth Age precedent, or that very Age in which it was held, ſo humble they are to ſubmit to any Authority that toucheth not the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions in preſent controverſie, but where do they find Chriſts Church ſhould be Judg in three Ages, and fail in the fourth, or that the Councels in the fifth Age ſhould be ſound, but not the Fathers.</p>
            <p>In his 9th. Chapter he pretendeth the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, is cauſe of his diviſion, becauſe they deſire communion, <hi>and cannot be admitted, but under the beleef, and practiſe of things contrary to their conſciences,</hi> of which two propoſitions,<note place="margin">Sect: <hi>4 5.</hi>
               </note> if the ſecond be not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the firſt is vain, and is as if a ſubject ſhould plead he were unjuſtly out-lawed, becauſe he doth not deſire it, now to prove the latter, he aſſumeth that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant is ready to conteſt his Negatives, by grounds that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36184:14"/>all good Chriſtians ought to be concluded by, what he means by that, I know not, for that they will convince their Negatives by any ground, a good Chriſtian ought to be concluded by, I ſee nothing leſs.</p>
            <p>What then wil they conteſt it by? all grounds a good <hi>Orthodox</hi> Chriſtian ought to be concluded by. If they anſwer in the Affirmative, we ſhall ask them whether <hi>Si quis Eccleſiam non audierit,</hi> be one of their grounds, and if they ſay no, we ſhall clearly diſprove their major, but then their defence is, if any ground, or <hi>Rule</hi> of it ſelf firm, and good, ſpeaketh nothing clearly of a poine in queſtion, they will conteſt that point by thoſe grounds, is not this a goodly excuſe?</p>
            <p>In his 11 Chapter he ſaith, we judg them, and deſpiſe them: as to the firſt I have often wondered, and do now, that men pretending to learning, and reaſon, ſhould therein charge us with want of charity, for if our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be falſe, it is error, not malice, and whether true, or falſe, we preſs it upon them, out of love and kindneſs, to keep them from the harm, that <hi>according to our beleef may come unto them:</hi> but ſince they deny they are ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and offer to prove it, we muſt not ſay it: yet I think we ought until we have cauſe to beleeve them, ſince our higheſt tribunal the Churches voice, from which we have no appeal, hath paſſed Judgment againſt them.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Chapter he compiaineth of the Catholicks for reproaching them with the loſs of their Church, and arguing with their Diſciples in this ſort, commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in ſome Church even externally, is neceſſary, but you cannot now communicate with your late Church for that hath no ſubſiſtence, therefore you ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Church from whence you went out, truly in this caſe I think they ought to pardon the Catholick,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36184:14"/>who hath, or undoubtedly is perſwaded he hath a promiſe for eternity to his Church, and experience in the execution of that promiſe for 16 Ages, in which none other can compare with him, and ſees another Church judged by one of the learnedſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heoker</hi> Ecle: poll cha. 5.</note> &amp; moſt prudent perſons confeſſedly that ever was amongſt them, to be a building likely to laſt but 80 years, to be now torn up by the roots, and this done by the ſame means by which it was ſetled, I ſay if this Catholick beleeve his eyes, he is at leaſt to be excuſed, and though I know the Doctor will reply his Church is ſtill in being, preſerved in Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Presbyters rightly ordained, yet let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how inconſequent this is, to what he hath ſaid before, for ask him how doth it remain in being, if there be no ſuch Biſhops, or Presbyters amongſt them, for his defence againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, that the ſecular authority hath power to make, and change Biſhops, and Presbyters; from whence it wil follow, that as they were ſet up by a ſecular authority, ſo are they pulled down, and un-biſhoped by another ſecular Authority, if it be ſaid the Parliament which pulled them down had not the 3. bodies requiſite to make a Parliament, no more had that which ſet them up, <hi>for the Lords Spirit was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both in Parlament and Convocation,</hi> ſo that there was as much authority to pul them down, as to ſet them up, <hi>but it will be replyed that though they are pulled down, yet are they ſtil Biſhops, viz: the character remains with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas what is their characters if their misſion of Preaching, and Teaching, be extinguiſhed, which follows their juriſdiction, which juriſdiction the Doct: makes ſubject to the ſecular authority, ſo that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever characters their Biſhops, &amp; Presbyters pretend to have, they have according to his principles no power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36184:15"/>the layity, and ſo no character can be made of any Biſhop as head, and Paſtor, and of the people as bodie, and flock, and conſequently their Church is gone; and this he does out of a word in <hi>Rufinus,</hi> which he ſuppoſeth to be taken in a ſpecial propriety of Law, wheras indeed that Authors knowledg in Grammar was not ſuch as ſhould neceſſarily exact any ſuch beleef, eſpecially learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men ſaying the contrary.</p>
            <p>But we account our ſelves Biſhops, and Prieſts not from an authority, dependant upon Princes, or inherited from <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> or new, but from <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; ſo ſhal ſtand, and continue whatſoever Princes, or ſecular powers decree; when they according to their Doctrines, and Arguments are not to wonder if they be thrown down by the ſame Authortly that ſet them up, &amp; as the Synagogue was a Church to have an end, ſo is this with theirs difference, that the Synagogue was a true Church in reference to a better, but this a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, and tyrannical one to puniſh a better, as concerning the Drs. prayer for Peace, &amp; communion, all good People wil joyn with him if he produce <hi>Fructus dignes penitentiae,</hi> eſpecially if he acknowledg the infallibility of the Church, and ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of the Pope, the former is explicated ſufficiently in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Books, the latter is expreſſed in the Councel of <hi>Florence,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>viz</hi> We deſire that the Holy Apoſtolical See, and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> have the primacie over all the World, and that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſucceſſor to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the Prince of the Apoſtles, and truly Chriſts Vicar, and head of the whole Church, and the Father, &amp; Teacher of all Chriſtians, and that there was given him in St <hi>Peter</hi> from Chriſt a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> power to feed, direct, ond govern the Catholick Church: ſo far the Councel: without obeying this, the Dr: is a Sciſmatick; &amp; without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the other an Heretick, but lee him joyn with us in theſe, all the reſt will follow.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, you have my ſence of Dr: <hi>Hammonds</hi> Book, in all the Particulars, which I think to the purpoſe, my time, nor the brevity fit for a Letter not permitting, I ſhould be more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodical, and do reſt, </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend and humble Servant. B. P. Bruxels</hi> 
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date> the 30 <hi>March,</hi> 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
